[Music]
welcome back to awakening from the
meaning crisis last time I finished the
discussion of wisdom and connected it to
enlightenment and argued for the wise
cultivation of lighten ment as our
deepest kind of existential response to
the meaning crisis a way in which we can
awaken from the meaning crisis I then
wanted to put that scientific model of
spirituality or lack of a better phrase
into discourse with some of these
central prophets of the meaning crisis
I'm using the word prophet of course as
it's used in the Old Testament sense I'm
talking about individuals who were
crucial for articulating the advent and
helping to propose or promise a response
to the meaning crisis I put a diagram on
the board I'm not going to reap it that
diagram on the board in which Heidegger
played a central role
there's many connections in there that I
will not be able to fully address I'll
point out and because some of the people
are there insofar as they help us
articulate their response not to be
examined for their own sake a couple of
major pointers I want to make out first
an apology I misspelled because of my
dysgraphia and I didn't realize it there
was something bothering me the whole
time about the diagram I misspelled
Heidegger I won't make that mistake
again I mentioned the work of Nishida in
the shot initially in the Kyoto school I
will talk briefly about nishitani here
but I won't be able to go into that in
depth I do intend to pursue this later
in another series I am putting together
I'm putting together a couple of series
to follow this one and I would like to
do a series that will include work on
the kyoto school series that i'm
entitled the god beyond God in which we
look at
all of these great non-theistic thinkers
within both eastern and western
traditions and things like be killed a
school that tried to bridge between them
so I will have to neglect to some degree
the curative school in this series but I
promise to follow it up more deeply in
another series I also mentioned Derrida
and I will not be able to talk very much
a problem maybe not even on all about
Derrida and deconstructionism I will
also address this again when I return in
the other series to God beyond God
especially when I'm going to talk about
the relationship between Derrida and
what's called negative theology so many
of you will be perhaps disappointed that
I don't talk too much about Derrida or
the ACOTA school I do promise to return
to that in another series that I am
currently working on so what I did I do
I sort of tried to give a quick
background did Heidegger I talked about
the importance of literal and-and-and
phenomenology and I pointed you to the
work of Sokolowski as a great
introduction and there's slow gonna back
to the things whose role and he does
write a book with the word crisis in its
title the crisis I think in what is it
in European science we talks and this is
basically he is pointing to the loss of
contact epistemology and he's trying to
get that contact back and this is done
through a reflective experience
introspection but through a reflective
experiential attention paid to the
structures and processes within our
experience and I pointed out how there's
two components in this there's the
intentional mental directedness noesis
and then there's the world disclosure
there's a deep correlation between them
this is the note and this is the new
EEMA the new esis and notice that that's
a term I've used also to describe
perspectival knowing right and
and the correlation between the noesis
and the no EEMA is very much right like
the agent arena relationship now we took
a look at heidegger's main criticism of
hospitals work had and heidegger's main
criticism is that hustlers work had not
really given given us back the missing
contact I would say that I mean
agreement with this I think Heidegger is
pointing to something very important in
the critique of phenomenology that
espero has picked up in his wonderful
book the end of phenomenology anyways
well suppose work had not given us a
contact but it has not really developed
adequately participatory knowing now I
do think that Marlow Ponte went a long
way towards addressing this he's after
Heidegger with his notion of embodiment
and I think I tried to explain how much
this notion of embodiment has been taken
up into cognitive science and how
intimately it is connected with the
return to contact epistemology in fact I
would argue that there is no return to a
contact epistemology without a deep
existential and theoretical recognition
of embodiment so Heidegger is critiquing
both the being active the lack of
participatory knowing and perhaps that's
addressed by merleau-ponty but there's a
further thing that I think Marlow Ponte
does not address that is also lacking
for Heidegger right is that
participatory knowing is not set with an
ontology it's not set within a deeper
understanding of being and how we come
into contact with being being as
realness is in in the sense of the
ground Ignis without which grounds truth
seems to be something that Hydra feels
that was lacking in Husserl's work
another way of putting it is that how do
they thought that HUS row was still
trapped within the Cartesian cultural
cognitive grammar was still trapped
within subjectivity and this is the main
thing that Sparrow criticizes throughout
his entire book there's also a YouTube
video by him that you can watch on his
critique of phenomenology that
phenomenology is driven by the goal of
returning to the things but because of
its approach it actually can never
return to the things it is still locked
into a kind of subjectivity or a hidden
kind of idealism that what is really
needed right to get to being is this
aspect of how to gear that I'm going to
talk about shortly which is to pay
attention to the independence of being
from our experience of it which is
something that a lot of people do not
tend to emphasize and Heidegger that's
largely because I think while it's
president Heidegger it's not made
explicit and foregrounded enough from
him but I think the work of speculative
realists like Harmon and others Morton
for example brings this aspect out and
why they see their work as transcending
phenomenology so how but now to return
to Heidegger how do we get to this
deeper contact well it's really
interesting that he tries to do he's
still within phenomenology but he's
trying to get it to drive towards
ontology get us back in touch with the
world and he's trying to get you to do
this through a specific kind of
questioning now this questioning you
have to think of this questioning as
taking place not in the having mode in
which we're trying to get an answer
trying to control the situation you have
to think of it much more as within the
be in mode a being mode that is
experienced as Wonder in fact perhaps a
better word is not questioning but
questing you're trying to go on a quest
with this questioning you're not trying
to have a propositional answer you're
trying to engage in a participatory
transformation now this brings us to the
central thing
for Heidegger in some ways and this is
Heidegger's notion of design being there
this is our being and notice notice how
this is an inheritance from the
Christian tradition that we're in the
image of God somehow by Heidegger is
taking this up as somehow by paying
attention by wandering into questing
into our being we will get a deeper
understanding of being itself why is
that because for Heidegger our being is
the being right whose being is in
question
we are the type of being who actually
question who and what we are in a way
that makes a difference
to who and what we are this is the core
idea of existentialism existentialism is
that we are fundamentally right without
an essence and that we are right our
essence if you want to put it that way
is to have no essence and therefore we
are continually defining ourselves by
how we question and right and we
question our being and respond to that
questioning question so the idea by
phenomenologically exploring that being
our design the way we are the being
whose being is in question we can
simultaneously come into contact with
our modal existence come into the being
mode and come into contact with the
mystery of beer now coming into contact
with this is central to Heidegger and
Heidegger is deeply responding to the
meaning crisis one of Heidegger is most
famous or perhaps
infamous theses the one that runs is a
constant thread throughout his work is
the this idea that the history of
metaphysics which Heidegger tends to use
in a pejorative term the history of
philosophical existential and perhaps
also religious responses
to design to the kind of the kind of
being we have the history of that
response is metaphysics and for
Heidegger the hit that history is the
history of nihilism Heidegger sees that
whole project has fundamentally
misconstrued to use our language the
whole project is a fundamental Mis
framing of our relationship to being and
because of that that has produced this
deep loss of contact with our being and
therefore simultaneously with being
itself and that for Heidegger is the
meaning crisis so this whole history
that we saw for example in the first
half of this series is the history of
nihilism and you can see I hope if you
remember that argument that there's a
lot of great truth in what Heidegger has
to say about how the unfolding of the
history of that metaphysical project has
led us into the meaning crisis now
Heidegger does not use the word ontology
in a pejorative way the way he uses the
word metaphysics most people don't have
this distinction as as clearly as
Heidegger stipulates it to be so when
we're talking about how do their
metaphysics is a pejorative term it is a
Mis framing of the ontological project
the ontological project is the project
of understanding our being and thereby
understanding our relation to being and
thereby understanding being itself so
there
I mean editors volumous who's incredibly
prolific he's also famously difficult to
read his wheats his works have an
operatic structure to them they often
fail to come to any clear conclusion
part of that I think is legitimate part
of that it right is him wrestling with
trying to break out of the cultural
cognitive grammar but I
so think and this is part of my
criticism of Heidegger part of it is
self-promotional by constantly being the
person for you know I'm now seeing that
these deep mysteries he also and how
difficult it is to think about them and
how he's exemplifying that difficulty
he's all he was also and I think it's
pretty clear this is part of what he's
doing he was also from those you can see
this from some of those who knew him
more intimately
he was also building a mystique around
himself so you have to take that into
account so all of that makes it
difficult to sort of point to here's
where I'm going to point to the core of
Heidegger right but I do think there's
something for me and for many other
people and I hope for you there there is
a particular place where I think we can
zero in on what Heidegger is doing and
this is his his his important essay on
evolve is in their VAR height which is
on the essence of truth and I think this
is important because it will tie into
many of the themes we have discussed I
want to read an extended quote from this
and then I'll comment on it so this is
the quote from Heidegger obviously
translated into English which is a
difficult task I've been told um you
have to read a lot of Heidegger before
you read Heidegger well because you will
miss read Heidegger for a long time and
part of why he makes his writing so
torturous is to sort of tear you out of
the mistake in ways you will
misunderstand him okay so here is the
translation a statement is invested with
its correctness so this is right a sense
of true when we say that statement is
true and we mean it's correct a
statement is invested with its
correctness by the openness of
comportment so I'm gonna try and unpack
all of this for you the openness of
comportment Howe right there's your how
you work imported towards things right
for only through the latter the openness
of compartment and I'll try to explain
to you what that means can what is
opened up be
what can what has opened up really
become the standard for the present ativ
correspondence okay so let's stop here
so here's the idea of truth as
correspondents a standard notion of
truth so the idea here is this is how
truth works here's a statement and what
makes it correct is that it corresponds
in some important way to reality what's
in the statement and what's in reality
right correspond that's what makes it
correct that's what it is to be true now
of course famously philosophers have
argued for a long time and many
different ways about with this
correspondences but what Heidegger is
trying to say is right that that debate
about the correspondence has missed
something and here's part of the MIS
framing it's missed that this
corresponding relationship is grounded
is depended on right and it's sustained
by a deeper relationship all right open
comportment Mutt let must let itself be
assigned the standard so this lower
relationship this open compartment is an
affordance of an ability to set up
correspondence between statements and
reality such that we find them true now
it's not to think about what this means
there must mean that in making the
statement the person is directed and
connected it also means that right the
statement is picking up on some aspect
of reality that it's disclosed and
there's some kind of connection there so
he's trying to point towards thus this
means that it must take over a pre given
standard for all presentation this
belongs to the openness of comportment
so the normative standard what we
normally call truth truth as correctness
as correspondence between statement and
reality right is ultimately grounded
dependence on how this deeper
relationship which we haven't quite
articulated yet our fords and makes
possible this but you can see something
here to use some of our language you can
see how the
agent and the arena have to be shaped to
each other such that what the agent does
or says is meaningful in that arena so
the agent arena relationship makes
possible and affords right this right
correctness but of course what hydrators
pointing to is yes but what grounds this
agent arena relationship now I've tried
to argue that it's ultimately the
process of relevance realization we're
going to come back to that Heidegger is
gonna I'm gonna argue that this is
relevance I've argued this is relevance
realization Heydrich talks about this in
terms of attunement he uses a tune mint
which is very nice because it picks up
on musicality so here's another quote by
Heidegger specifically mention this
however being attuned attunement can
never be understood as experience notice
what he's saying here acumen can never
be understood as experience and feeling
he is rejecting any subjective
interpretation of entombment why because
to continue it is there by simply
deprived of its essence you have lost
the essence of attunement if you
understand its subjectively
it is not an experience it is something
that makes meaningful experience
possible and I argue that that of course
was the case right for relevance
realization let's continue his quote
being attuned that is what he calls Eck
distant standing out exposing us so this
standing out he spreads he takes the
word existence and does it's sort of he
plays with words a lot and just does
this is standing out which of course is
analogous to how what the word salient
means standing out this existent expose
it Ness
nothing's right expose it 'no stew ba
this is us right as a whole can be
experienced and felt and he puts both of
those words in sort of scare quotes to
question them only because the man who
experiences again in question because
he's challenging this whole natural way
of thinking and talking that's what it's
putting it all in these scare quotes
right with without being aware of the
essence of attunement is always engaged
in being in tune in a way that discloses
beings as a whole right so attunement is
not subjective any subjective feeling or
experience of it is actually grounded in
the attuning relationship that precedes
and grounds our cognitive appraisal or
appropriation within the agent arena
relationship okay so because we have got
locked up here what I would call the
propositional level we have forgotten
this we have forgotten the attunement
relationship which for Heidegger is the
essence of truth because it's what makes
correctness of statements possible for
us because of this forgetfulness there's
another quote man clings to what is
readily available and controllable ever
while we're even sorry man clings to
what is readily available and
controllable even we're ultimate matters
are concerned remember that we're
ultimate when we come back to Tillich
please so what happens right is we get
trapped into the having of propositions
we get trapped into the having mode all
right what is readily available and
controllable there's a deep modal
confusion at this deep existential level
the forgetting of the grounding
attunement also traps us with
improvisational processing and and it
traps us it's in the having mode the
having of correct
positions and this goes right back right
this goes right back to Plato I don't
think I did it would like me doing this
his attitude towards Plato is very
ambivalent right you know Plato
consistently makes a distinction between
Philo phyleus ophea right the love of
wisdom and Phi Leah
Nakia right the love of victory the love
of victory the having of the correct
answer that defeats the opponent and
when one of Plato's like ongoing points
is this is the deepest kind of
bullshitting because this looks like
we're arguing this looks like we're
reasoning right but what we're doing is
manipulating propositions right and
trying to assert corrective nough sand
we're forgetting the pursuit of wisdom
the transforms transformative
existential project that Socrates
advents for us this is why I continually
criticize people who I suspect present
themselves as if they're doing this but
are often doing this this is why I am so
critical of people who want to debunk
demolish and debate to the point of
victory their opponents people who
really are incapable of getting out of
modal confusion they cannot remember the
being mode because right they can't
listen look this is house you know
somebody's listening they will say I did
not know that I have just learned
something from you or I was wrong I was
mistaken about this those are the marks
of phyleus ophea Heidegger is trying to
get us to remember Philae Oh Sophia and
he definitely sees the history of
metaphysics is becoming more and more
bound up of Philae an Ikea the pursuit
of victory the ultimate theory that
crushes all opposition so
we have to wake up for according to
Heidegger and again this is why his
language is so torturous because we are
in a state of deep forgetfulness deep
mortal confusion and if we read his text
we are deeply tempted to read them from
that forgetfulness and that modal
confusion and thereby fundamentally
misunderstand him so his texts are write
deliberately Socratic in there they're
constantly trying to undermine that
right that cognitive cultural grammar
that we habitually bring to things so he
wants us to remember sati The Forgotten
mystery of design so he says this
whenever the concealment of being as
whole is conceded only as a limit that
occasionally announces itself concealing
as a fundamental occurrence has sunk
into forgetfulness if we only sort of
acknowledge the way beings transcend our
framing of them sort of at the limit yes
yes yes their reality is combinatorial
explosive yes yes yes yes ah and we've
hit her back and we wave our hands and
then we go back - yes but within this
within my framework bla bla bla bla
right and what Heidegger says is right
when you only acknowledge it as a limit
you have actually deeply forgotten it
that relationship to the combinatorial
explosive nature of things has to be a
ongoing feature of your thinking now I
try to argue for this within the
relevance realization framework which
I'm going to show you is deeply
appropriate to Heidegger in terms of
this idea of sacredness as a as an acted
enacted participatory right resonance to
the mourners the inexhaustible Ness of
reality in order to pick this up I want
to briefly because as I said I can't go
into this a great deal I hope to go into
this again later and
in another series but I want to briefly
talk about the work of Hartmann and
what's called object-oriented ontology
or what's also known as speculative
realism and this is the position from
which Sparrow and Harmon and others have
critique phenomenology as being
inadequate so what's again trying to
summarize all of this which is like some
of the most exciting work that's
recently being done in ontology you know
and I and I respect people who say we
need to talk about ontology more but if
you want to talk about ontology just
don't do old talk about ontology pay
attention to the insightful inventive
new work being done on ontology within
speculative realism so again I I
wouldn't even claim this as a summary
I'm just picking up one important thread
of the speculative realism as a way of
trying to develop this important idea of
Heidegger and because we're gonna need
it when we talk about other people like
you know Tillich and young and Barfield
so the core of this is not the contine
picture of the thing in itself veiled by
subjectivity right so remember that
content picture right right our
subjectivity completely veils the thing
in itself and makes it ultimately
inaccessible to us
so what Hartmann and speaking up on is
that this transient and we'll come back
to see that there's a difficulty there
they have a difficulty with limiting
ontology to what they call correlation
just our experience of ontology but
nevertheless let's start here this
transient makes both the subject and the
object possible in experience right in
phenomenological experience
so what does that mean well there's a
different way about thinking about how
you encounter objects right instead of
the Contin thing in itself that is
veiled from us by our subjectivity
instead think about two things happening
simultaneously this is picking up on
what Heidegger is talking about think
about the thing shining into
subjectivity and that's what
phenomenology originally means how do
their picks up on that the Greek term
phenomenon actually means to shine forth
so simultaneously the thing is shining
into my subjectivity but that is
interpenetrated inter afforded with it
is simultaneously withdrawing from my
framing it is always beyond my framing
as well and that that beyond this is not
something in my phenomenology but it
contributes to the sense of the realness
of my phenomenological experience right
think about how in virtual reality
when there if the world if you get a
sense that the world is closed if that
you can drain it dry with your activity
it loses its realness but only and
here's now the openness that kiters
talking about the compartment but only
if there's a realness a way in which the
world withdraws beyond you continually
right so things there's always a horizon
of your experience a horizon is
something you always move towards but
you can never reach right so as long as
that world constantly withdraws as it
also shines into your experience then it
is real to you now the morning is not
something in your experience it's not an
object of your experience but it's a
feature that withdrawal is as much a
contributor to the realness of things as
they're shining into your subjectivity
this is I think a profound way in which
harman and others have explicate 'add
heidegger's idea and then gone beyond it
now
the way I want to put it and the way
I've argued it right earlier is this I
think this lines up with what I've tried
to argue that our framing which is trans
ejected in nature about attunement
simultaneously discloses and conceals
right so I want to replace the content
term the thing in itself with another
way another term the thing beyond itself
everything is both shining into our
subjectivity and withdrawing beyond our
framing of it and those are inter
affording their interpenetrating they co
contribute to the realness of the object
for us and it's precisely that
withdrawing according to Harman and
others that was missed by phenomenology
because of the way it was still bound
within a Cartesian subjective framework
whether or not that is completely fair
to phenomenology is another question and
I'm not trying to get into that
theoretical debate right here my main
focus here is trying to understand
what's going on but I think we can take
from speculative realism this idea this
term I've coined the thing beyond itself
it's clearly a central idea in in
Harmons idea of the object the thing
beyond itself okay so this takes us to
now a new understanding of truth how do
we get an attunement that discloses
things as things beyond themselves
things that are simultaneously shining
in and into our subjectivity but and in
right but also withdrawing into their
objectivity where this no longer means
an object of thought it means a depth
beyond our framing and independence
beyond our experience and how those are
transgender penetrating for us in the
sense of realism what does it mean to be
connected to things in this way and this
is Heidi there's famous notion
of truth as Alafaya truth is Alafaya
so late they means - it means to cover
or to forget the in the in Greek
mythology the underworld you pass
through the river Leyte and it made you
forget all of your previous life as you
went into the underworld and this is of
course the negation of it so means sort
of a deep remembering it's a te and a
deep disclosure so always remember these
two poles it's a deep remembering you
have to modally remember not just like
our normal sense of remember it like
sati you have to remember the being mode
and this disclose is right this aspect
of reality that it is simultaneously
shining and withdrawing so truth is all
affair is this right a tuning to the
mutual disclosure fitted mystery of
being so right you're getting attuned to
things you you're deeply remembering
things and again not just cognitive
memory existential memory you're
remembering things this is to be in
contact with them when you're attuned to
how they are simultaneously appearing
shining and withdrawing all right now
I've been through out using the language
of relevance realization that I've
argued for to talk about Heidegger and
some of you may be a little bit sort of
like I don't like that you know
Heidegger is you know you know I like
the harder you're talking it's all
ontological and I don't want this
scientific talk and you know and you
might have a deeper point there because
the scientific talk for Heidegger is at
a higher level than ontology
nevertheless
I want to continue to making this
argument and I want to make it because
there's an explicit and important
history and this is the connection that
has had a profound impact on my work and
the argument that you have seen between
Heidegger Herbert Dreyfuss
and third-generation
third-gen 4e oxide that I have
articulated and exemplified to you
Dreyfus is an important interpreter of
Heidegger but he's also one of the
founding figures of this version of
cognitive science in fact Dreyfus tried
to formulate or is continuing to
formulate important aspects of third
generation for ACOG in of science as a
way of trying to articulate the
importance of Heidegger for
understanding the nature of mind the
nature of cognition the nature of
consciousness etc so there's a book he
wrote on heidegger's most central work
being in time and a dreyfuses book is
called being in the world and I want to
read you a quote for that and the quote
is exemplary it's not a unique isolated
moment in Dreyfuss work it's something
that is exemplary of a theme running
throughout Dreyfuss here's the quote
from that book on Heidegger okay quote
facts and rules are by themselves
meaninglessness to capture what
Heidegger calls significance or
involvement they must be assigned
relevance and those two terms are
emphasized in the original my emphasis
of them are is just reporting the
emphasis that he gave them they must be
assigned relevance but the predicates
that must be added to define relevance
right are just more meaningless facts
you can't capture it with the definition
and paradoxically the more facts the
computers right
are given so the more facts the computer
is given notice how he shot he
immediately leaks Heidegger to a
computational psychology and the
critique of it alright the more facts
the computer is given the harder it is
to compute what is relevant to the
current situation you get into
combinatorial explosion if you stay at
the propositional computational level
and you lose your ability to fit
yourself to the current situation to
cope with the current situation this is
why Dreyfuss because of Heidegger was
one of the has was one of the founding
and remains one of the ongoing critics
of a cup eur a purely computational
cartesian approach to cognitive science
to AI to artificial intelligence he
literally wrote the book entitled what
computers can't do that founded this
whole right criticism of computational
psychology it's considered the discovery
of the frame problem within cognitive
science he later updated it with a later
book called what computers still can't
do this has been an ongoing thing he
sees Heidegger as the deep floor Runner
of the criticism that we should
understand the mind only in
propositional computational terms this
is why Dreyfuss went on to pick up also
work from Marla Ponte which I've
referenced and helped to develop right
this notion of an optimal grip that I've
discussed that length right optimal grip
as a process that is doing this
relevance realization and it is
something that is deeper than
propositional knowing so I'm trying to
show you that right my attempts to
connect Heidegger who is a prophet of
the meaning crisis to the machinery of
relevance realization and participatory
knowing an optimal gripping is not
misplaced Dreyfuss is not a single
figure there are other figures
like this see the work by Dreyfus and
Charles Taylor retrieving realism about
how we can get back to really be in
contact by making use of these ideas I'm
going to keep doing that I'm gonna keep
showing you because what I'm trying to
show you is that the framework we have
built allows us to enter into deep
dialogue with the central prophets of
the meaning crisis in a way that I think
insightfully discloses aspects of their
own theorizing and affords potential
eason optically integrating them
together into a more comprehensive
response to the meaning crisis this is
the final part of the argument I'm
making I want to continue on do a little
bit more about Heidegger and leading
into the other thinkers we want to
examine so evens in his wonderful book
the new gnosis in which he talks about
Heidegger Corbin Jung Hillman right it's
a book in which he links Heidegger to
korban into Jung and he puts it this way
when he's discussing Heidegger's thought
okay here's a quote again it picks up on
something we've already been talking
about here's the quote a questioning
that involves the questionnaire in the
matter of thought so deeply he becomes
in a sense one with it at the point at
this point knowing is no longer divorced
from being we know the way we are and we
are the way we know in the Platonic
tradition this is expressed in the axiom
light can only be known by like he is
pointing directly and this is not
something you get in Heidegger but
that's why I turned to avens right he's
pointing to how Heidegger's actually
bringing back this deeply in the
Neoplatonic know in platonic idea right
of knowing of participatory knowing as a
deep kind of karna forma t between you
and the world
and this is a participatory knowing that
is a dynamic coupling now even's
immediately points and connects this
kind of participatory knowing this
dynamic coupling like knowing by like
and reality is dynamic so you have to be
dynamic and dynamically coupled to it
right he immediately points from
Heidegger to korben korben is deeply
influenced by how to grow Corbin was one
of the first important translators of
Heidegger into French his translation of
introduction to metaphysics was seminal
for how Heidegger was spread into France
for example but high Corbin explicitly
calls this participatory knowing that is
a dynamical coupling a dynamical
conformity right he explicitly calls
this gnosis term we've already examined
right gnosis for Corbin this is quote is
a here's the quote a salvation all
redemptive knowledge because it has the
virtue of bringing about the inner
transformation of man sorry for the
sexist language on his part it is
knowing that quote changes and
transforms the knowing subject you see
it's that dynamical coupling in which
you know by being coupled to something
and it's participatory knowing because
you know it insofar as you are changed
and your knowing of yourself and your
knowing of the object are coupled
together but that is what you need to
respond appropriately to Jacques design
look you are the being who's being in
question and by questing into that you
quest into being you are only going to
get a response to that quest when you
add something that simultaneously in an
inter penetrative into a 14 fashion is
both knowing yourself not your
autobiographical knowing knowing the
depths of your being knowing yourself
and knowing the world coupled together
mutually affording each other that this
is what Corbin is calling gnosis and
this is what he's saying he's getting
from Heidegger now let's take a look at
what we've done so far
and I want to show you how these two
things are not right irrelevant they're
deeply relevant to each other
you've got Dreyfus over here and the
whole aspect of relevance realization
and Dreyfus is clearly pointing out that
this is no on Proposition all coming
from Heidegger non-computational in the
sense where computation is the
inferential manipulation of propositions
to dry out implication relations and
then over here you have Corbin and he's
calling all of this gnosis this
participatory mutually self and world
transformative kind of knowing but what
Corbin is doing with the gnosis that
isn't apparent in Dreyfus is that he's
pointing out how this is redemptive how
it saves us right remember the Gnostics
are trying to free us to liberate us
from existential entrapment so Corbin is
pointing out that how this Corbett is
making explicit that this machinery that
we're talking about here is a way of
responding to the modal confusion it is
a way of responding to the forgetfulness
of being it is a way of awakening from
the meaning crisis so let's try and do
this again a little bit more carefully
so I do this a little bit more carefully
what is this forgetfulness this modal
confusion okay so on one hand we have
the being load and remember from
ultimately gets this from Heidegger as
does Steven bachelor being mowed the
having mode do you see what I'm trying
to do though I'm trying to show you how
seamlessly you can interleave this
language right from Heidegger with the
language we've been developing in the
second half of this series okay so the
being mode so what's going on in the
being mode the being mode is the
transformative participation in the
mystery of being okay that
transformative participation and the
mystery of being right this leads of
course to Alafaya which I've discussed
right
and there's two components to this that
we've discussed
there's the attunement right but there's
also the independence of being
right I think the attunement clearly
points to relevance
I've already argued that repeatedly I
hope I don't have to argue it anymore
but this independence of being this is
independent right of the correlation
between us and being that being always
transcends how it is being known and
being experienced by us this is the more
nests that withdrawal that is
simultaneously present and so that's
what I almost made a mistake sorry about
that right the more nests is
simultaneously with the presence of the
shining right this I think is what
Harmon and others would argue ultimately
gives things what I don't want to say
all of their realness but an important
pole of their realness that we have
neglected so you can see what I'm trying
to point there's I mean the word I would
you know it might even seem natural to
put here right of the independence of
being its truth but that's not quite
right right because we've seen that
truth belongs up here in the discussion
of Alafaya or even higher up in the
correctness of our propositions based on
Alafaya right so this is relevance and
what am i stopping here because remember
we don't want to confuse relevance and
we don't want to disconnect relevance
from truth or realness right and I want
to put to something deeper here that the
relevance must always be right open to
and not remember not just as an
acknowledgement as a limit it has to be
an ongoing constraint the relevance has
to have an ongoing constraint right in
its connectedness to a sense of the more
nests the inexhaustible nests
of the thing beyond itself
so what would be going on over here in
the having mode and where we're getting
the modal confusion so now we think of
an object we think of its being in terms
of how it can be manipulated by us not
just physically conceptually remember
this is the the quintessential point of
the having mode we have control we can
we can grasp it we can manipulate it we
can use it we're not confronting
mysteries we're solving problems and so
what happens when we get into the having
mode into conceptual manipulation and
the halving of propositions and we
forget the being mode and all of this
over here what can happen to us
well and this is one of hydras main
critiques we start to miss understand in
a modal sense you start to misunderstand
being as a right particular being we
misunderstand being as a being so I'm
using being as a with a capital B to
being being where I'm using a little B
to mean a particular being like this you
know marker or this eraser or this body
right
and then we misunderstand the attempt to
try and get back to this by positing it
with it this is a modal confusion we try
to capture which with something's wrong
just thinking we're not quite getting
being with a big B when we look at this
being or think of being as a particular
we've got to do something more and so it
we'll do is we'll put it to the limit
I remember what Heidegger says that's
insufficient we'll understand being
right as right as the Supreme Being the
highest being the highest subject
perhaps the highest person the highest
force the highest thing and for
Heidegger this is the ultimate modal
confusion for this is to try to turn
being in a problem being into a problem
that can be solved by the conceptual
right manipulation of a propositional a
defined object and of course what's
being alluded to here is classical
theism z' sort of traditional
presentation of God now whether or not
this is going to be fair to how many
people have just written about God we're
gonna come back to that when we talk
about Tillich and Barfield Heidegger is
certainly right that there is a
long-standing tradition within
metaphysics understood in a pejorative
sense in which God is understood in this
limit sense God is understood within the
having mode God is understood as the
Supreme Being that somehow grounds and
makes right all other beings and this is
a fundamental mistake for Heidegger
there's a fundamental misunderstanding
it's a fundamental problem so this is
known as the problem of Anto theology
where we try to understand being
theologically in terms of a Supreme
Being and for Heidegger that and this
may strike many of you who come from
religious framework as you know almost
bordering on offensive I'm trying I'm
trying to present in a way I think
that's more accessible to you that's not
the case right but what Heidegger is
saying I'm sorry it's not the case that
I what I I misspoke there it's not the
case that you should simply I'm sorry
I'm not I'm stating something where I
should be requesting something that's
why I'm stumbling I'm requesting of you
that you are not simply offended that
you try and understand what Heidegger is
trying to articulate here right because
he's going to make this claim and here's
the claim that you might find offensive
that there's a deep connection between
the understanding of being in terms of
the Supreme Being God Anto theology and
nihilism this is this is Heidi to try to
articulate nietzsche and reaches another
big influence on how to do understanding
being or the ground of being as a
supreme being on to theology is the deep
forgetfulness that just cause us
existentially right adrift in modal
confusion and fundamentally miss framing
our relationship to to being and
therefore being subject to a
disconnectedness from realness which is
at the heart with the meaning crisis so
Tillich is going to pick this up gonna
be deeply influenced by hiding it but
also I think I'd prefer Tillich to
Heidegger and there's also personal
reasons for that Tillich was the first
non-jewish academic to be basically well
persecuted by the Nazis because he from
the very beginning opposed them and
resisted them he had to leave Germany
because of that unlike Heidegger and
this is not something you should dismiss
like some people do and I want to return
to it discuss it later
Heidegger joins the Nazi Party and
becomes an official member
an official within the Nazi Party and
that is something to pay attention to
and it's fair to bring this up because
Heidegger presents his
entire position as an existential one
not just a theoretical one and if you
try to dismiss his participation in the
Nazis by just saying oh but that has
nothing to do with his theory you have
sort of fundamentally missed how he is
involved with the very presentation of
his own theory
now Tillich is gonna take up
nevertheless Heidegger's critique of
Anto theology but he's going to do
something very interesting with it he's
going to use this as a way of bringing
back the very traditional religious
notion of idolatry and what is wrong
with idolatry so next time what I would
like to explore with you as a way of
developing further what Corbin is
talking about with gnosis and gnosis as
serious play I want to try to finish up
what would it be like to have the gnosis
to remember to remember being through
Alafaya what would it be like to be
remembering being threal affair what
would that be like how would we be how
would the world be to us and this is a
way of trying to say what it would be
like to experience the remembering that
is a way of awakening from the meaning
crisis thank you very much for your time
and attention
[Music]
you